Guide to the Park West Village Tenants Association Records TAM.333
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Park West Village Tenants Association Records
1950-2022
1980-2007
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Park West Village Tenants Association (New York, N.Y.)
Armstrong, Winifred
DeMeio, Albina
TAM.333
23.5 Linear Feet in 21 record cartons, 5 manuscript boxes, and 1 folder in shared housing
The Park West Village Tenants Association Records document the organized activities of tenants in seven apartment buildings on New York City's Upper West Side. The apartments were built as part of a government-subsidized urban redevelopment plan in the late 1950s and consist of four buildings on Central Park West and three building on Columbus Avenue (372, 382, 392, 400 Central Park West, and 784, 788, 792 Columbus Avenue). The association preserves the rent stabilized, middle income status of residents in the buildings, to ensure the proper maintenance of the property, and protect the rights of individual tenants. The collection contains administrative files of the Park West Village Tenants Association (PWVTA), including board meeting notes, agendas, and membership lists. Other materials relate to the work of individual members of PWVTA, many of which held leadership positions within the organization. The collection also contains ephemera produced by the PWVTA, which includes flyers for meetings and events, tenant association newsletters, and other ephemeral more generally related to tenants' rights.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Albina DeMeio and Winifred Armstrong on behalf of the Park West Village Tenants Association in 2004; additional materials were donated by the Park West Village Tenants Association in 2010, and by Winifred Armstrong in 2016, January 2020, June 2022, and April 2025. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 2004.034, 2010.017, 2016.017, 2016.047, 2020.016, 2023.056, and 2025.050.
Arrangement
Documents in this collection are grouped roughly by subject or by creator, and described at the box-level. A brief inventory has been created to provide an overview of the contents of each box.
Historical Note
The Park West Village Tenants Association represents the tenants of seven apartment buildings on New York City's Upper West Side (372, 382, 392, 400 Central Park West, and 784, 788, 792 Columbus Avenue), built as part of a government-subsidized urban redevelopment plan in the late 1950s. The four Central Park West buildings have become condominiums. The Association seeks to preserve the rent stabilized, middle income status of the three remaining rental buildings, to ensure the proper maintenance of the property, and protect the rights of individual tenants of the buildings, and the tenants as a whole.
Custodial History
The archived website was migrated from the California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service to the Internet Archive's Archive-It Service in November 2015. The link to California Digital Library was removed in October 2017.
Scope and Contents
The Park West Village Tenants Association Records document the organized activities of tenants in the seven buildings of the Park West Village on Manhattan's Upper West Side. The collection contains administrative files of the Park West Village Tenants Association (PWVTA), including board meeting notes, agendas, and membership lists. Materials in this collection document PWVTA's negotiations with building owners and real estate companies regarding various housing issues between the late 1980s and the early 1990s. Topics they address include discussions over the construction of a road through the complex in 1993, the conversion to condominiums, and a battle over rent reductions and major capital improvements that lasted from 1993 to 2005. Several boxes in the collection relate to the work of individual members of PWVTA, many of which held leadership positions within the organization. The collection also contains ephemera produced by the PWVTA, which includes flyers for meetings and events, tenant association newsletters, and other ephemeral more generally related to tenants' rights.
Two boxes of materials donated in 2016 include documents related to the work of Park West Village historian and former PWVTA president Winifred Armstrong. These materials date from the late 1980s to 2000 and consist of tenant association newsletters (1993-1997), flyers, pamphlets on tenants' rights, correspondence with real estate agencies, tenant association memoranda, and membership and contact lists from the late 1980s. Other materials include notes, correspondence, memos and bulletins, and internal documents related to the conversion of buildings at 392 and 400 Central Park West into condominiums, campaigns in support of rent controls, and tenant complaints to building managers in the 1980s.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
Tenants' associations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Landlord and tenant -- New York (N.Y.); Upper West Side (New York, N.Y.); Housing policy -- New York (State) -- New York.; Housing -- New York (N.Y.); Rent control -- New York (State) -- New York; Park West Village Tenants Association (New York, N.Y.); Armstrong, Winifred; DeMeio, Albina
- Proposed Changes and Rent Reduction/Major Capital Investment Battle, 1990s-2005 (Box 1)
  Scope and Content Note
  Contains letters dated July 13 and August 11, 1993 concerning a roadway to be constructed on the property including buildings 372, 382, 392 and 400 Central Park West (CPW); A renters guide prepared by PWVTA in September 1992; Copies of covenants concerning the building of Park West Village; The Black Book and other papers pertaining to the Condominium Offering Plan for 392 CPW; The detailed history of the rent reduction and MCI battle between the tenants of 784, 788 and 792 Columbus Ave which began in 1993 and was finally settled in 2005.
- Executive Board Minutes and Agendas and Early PWVTA Documents, 1980s-1990s (Box 2)
  Contains Executive Board minutes and agendas 1991-1992; Legal material re: Balconies in 400 Central Park West (CPW); Fences Fight in CPW buildings in the early 1990s; PWVTA Membership lists 1993-1995, all seven buildings, and letters re conversion; CPW 400 Awning 1995; Early conversion material: brad brewwer argument, survey 5/28/1984, Court Case 372/382; Newsletters 1982-1988; Election 1991; Harassment casev (ambriose) 400 CPW; Roy Harris eviction case, mostly from 792 and 400 in 2000.
- Newsletters, 1990s (Box 3)
  Contains issues of Red Tailed Hawk 1994-1996; Fence issue, CPW buildings; Newsletters - assorted files for 372 CPW and other issues in the 1990s
- Fliers and Newsletters; Board Meeting Notes, undated (Box 4)
  Contains fliers and newsletters; Some board meeting notes and agendas (Note: many duplicates)
- General Files, 1990s (Box 5)
  Contains general records - mainly 372 Central Park West
- Intercom Files: 784, 788, 792 Columbus Ave, 1990s (Box 6)
  Contains intercom Files -784, 788, 792 Columbus Ave; Division of Housing and Community Renewal (DHCR) Rent Reduction Petitions, Complaints, Legal Documents; Tenant Window Depositions; Newsletters, Fliers
- Division of Housing and Community Renewal (DHCR) Legal Documents, 1990s (Box 7)
  Contains Division of Housing and Community Renewal (DHCR) legal documents: Complaints, PAR Exhibits, Security Remands re 784, 788, 792 Columbus Ave; Robert J. Anderson's Comments
- Legal Materials, 1994-2000 (Box 8)
  Contains legal materials: Security Reduction; Window MCI's
- Legal Materials, 1994-2000 (Box 9)
  Contains legal materials: Screening Rent Reductions, Window MCI at 792 Columbus Ave
- Bess Mitchell Files, 1980s-1990s (Box 10)
  Bess Mitchell Files, including Harassment Case, Board Meetings, mostly from 400 CPW
- Conversion of 392 and 400 Central Park West, 1989-2000 (Box 11)
  Conversion of 392/400 CPW - including correspondence with Attorney General's Office 1989-1992; Vivian Dee Files (President) 2000-2002
- Vivian Dee Files and Florence Wagener Files, 2000-2004 (Box 12)
  Vivian Dee Files (President) 2000-2002; Overcharge Cases /Division of Housing and Community Renewal Settlement from 784-788-792 Columbus Ave (Florence Wagener Files): Aptaker, Lisa; Anderson, Linda; Anthony, Peter; Fackler, Peter H. 2000-2004
- Florence Wagener Files and Division of Housing and Community Renewal Settlement, 2000-2004 (Box 13)
  Overcharge Cases from 784-788-792 Columbus Ave (Florence Wagener Files)/ Division of Housing and Community Renewal Settlement: Feldman, Jason; Fleck, Richard; Kantor, Molly; Glowski, Matt; Lammers, Brent; Nack, Jessica; Nakaniski, Yuki; Pace, William; Purdy, Colin; Rose, Lisa; Resnick, Adam; Santora, Frank; Sorotzkin, Steven; Stepanchek, Tom; Squillacioti, Kathleen; Velyvis, Peter; Williamson, John; Zuckerman, John; Wangh, Anne
- Consolidated DHCR Overcharge Cases and Dan Dunbar Files, 1996-2007 (Box 14)
  Consolidated DHCR Overcharge Cases (Note: DHCR Final Order is confidential - owner payments may not be quoted but Rent Rollback can be) 2002-2005; Dan Dunbar Files: administrative documents, newsletters, etc. 1997-2007
  Access Restrictions
  DHCR Final Order is confidential - owner payments may not be quoted but Rent Rollback can be
- Dan Dunbar Files and Legal Files, 1988, 1996-2007 (Box 15)
  Dan Dunbar Files: administrative documents, newsletters, etc. 1996-2007; 400 Central Park West Black Book and 792 Complaint Forms; Legal Files - mainly from Dean Hefner: File 1. Diminution of Services, Comp Agreement drafts, Rent Strike, File 2. MCI 1992-2002, File 3. DHCR Consolidated Overcharge Case 2005; 400 Central Park West Roof Repair and Rent Decrease Case from Winifred Armstrong 198
- Legal Files: Early and Current Cases, 1950s-2006 (Box 16)
  Legal Files: Early and Current Cases: File 4. Property Agreements, 1950s, Certificates of Occupancy of 784, 788, 792, including parking; Harassment Case 1987, Challenge to Condo Case 1984, Hardship Case 1979; File 5 injunction 2006; File 6 MCI 2004-2006; Legal Files from Sylvia Friedrich
- Parking Case: DHCR Decision, 1989 (Box 17)
- Winifred Armstrong Files (Editor of PWVTA Newsletter) and Vicki Lawrence Papers, 1980s-1990s; 18 Linear Feet (18 boxes) (Box 18)
  Administrative documents, fliers, correspondence; Winifred Armstrong Files (Editor of PWVTA Newsletter); Vicki Lawrence Papers, includes Condo Case 1984
- Tenants Issues, 1978-2006 (Box 19)
  Proposed road thru PWV at 99th St., 1993; Disputed Fence & Awning, 1993; Land Use, 2005-6; Proposed welcome pamphlet, 1996; Playground, 1988-2001; Apartment registrations, 2003; Rent overcharge, 2001-2004; Hardship case, 1978
- Winifred Armstrong Files, 1985-2000; 2016.017 (Box 20)
- Tenant Issues and Conversion of 392 and 400 Central Park West, 1984-1990 (Box 21)
  Scope and Contents
  This box contains correspondence, bulletins, newsletters, and meeting notes related to a variety of tenant concers in the late 1980s. Thse concerns include security, aspestos, membership, laundry. A large portion of the materials in this box also include bulletins, correspondence and complaints related to the conversion of the buildings at 392 and 400 Central Park West into condominiums.
- Parking Case, 2008-2013 (Box 22, Folder 1-7)
  This box contains materials documenting the PWVTA 2011-2014 parking case, including drawings, maps, correspondence, photographs of parking garages, legal filings, and applications forwork permits.
- Parking Case, 2008-2013 (Box 23, Folder 1-7)
  This box contains materials documenting the PWVTA 2011-2014 parking case, including diagrams, petitions, correspondence, legal filings, and public hearing minutes.
- Parking Case, 2008-2013 (Box 24, Folder 1-4)
  This box contains materials documenting the PWVTA 2011-2014 parking case, including petitions, memoranda, contracts, correspondence, legal filings, and summaries of the case.
- Administrative Records and Ephemera, 1984-2017 (Box 25)
  This box contains administrative records and ephemera, including flyers, small publications, correspondence, and meeting agendas and minutes. This box also contains documents related to 808 Columbus Avenue and the collapse of 784 Columbus Avenue.
- Administrative Records and Newsletters, 1986-2017 (Box 26)
  This box contains newsletters and documentation of neighborhood concerns, including the preservation of Central Park North, the collapse of 784 Columbus Avenue, and rent challenges and overcharges.
- Press Release: Winifred Armstrong "Woman of Distinction" Award, 2022 (Box Shared Tamiment 165, Folder 13)
- Archived Website, Mar 13, 2012-ongoing
  Park West Village Tenants' Association, first active in 1974, is a voluntary, non-profit, membership organization whose purposes are to protect the rights and welfare of tenants in Park West Village (PWV); keep PWV tenants informed of their rights; represent PWVTA members in negotiations with Park West managements; represent the concerns of PWVTA members to outside organizations and to elected officials and government agencies; and support and participate in campaigns by various organizations; to expand tenant rights; strengthen rent regulations; preserve affordable housing programs; and protect the ability of low-income and moderate-income tenants to remain in their homes. They are affiliated with Tenants and Neighbors and the Metropolitan Council on Housing. The website contains resources, a renters' guide, photos, and history.